Okay, so let's talk about some risk
response strategies, then.
In this case, we're
going to be talking about
risk response strategies
for a negative risk.
All right, now, let's look at what we've
done so far.
So we first planned our risk management
process, right?
So plan risk management, right,
the name of the process.
And we were creating, right, the artifact
that's created is the risk management
plan, documenting how, documenting
procedures.
Through our project, we're
also going to be identifying
our risk and then
updating the risk register.
We also talked about
qualitative risk analysis
and quantitative risk
analysis in previous videos.
So where we are ranking our risk,
prioritizing our risk, and then in
quantitative, actually adding a dollar
value to our risk.
Okay, so now that we've
identified all of these risks
and done all the analysis
and everything, now what?
well we need to respond to the risk right
we need to figure out how are we actually
going to respond to the risk right it's no
good just identifying a risk and then not
doing anything about it no we need to know
how to respond right so we have these risk
response strategies there are five risk
response strategies for a negative risk or
a threat then on a separate video we're
also going to be talking about five risk
response strategies for a
positive risk or an opportunity
All right, so let's look
at this first, negative risk.
So the first response strategy then,
escalate.
And escalate is literally as it sounds.
You escalate it to a higher authority.
As a project manager, you don't have the
authority to make a decision on this risk.
You've identified this major risk, but you
don't have the authority
to make that decision.
So who does?
You have to escalate it, escalate it to
higher authority.
So it's a very simple example.
At the beginning of 2020, right,
we had this whole COVID situation.
So, well, we had the start of the COVID
situation, right?
Project managers, at that point,
a lot of project managers for many
projects did not have
the authority to make a
decision, right, when that
COVID situation started.
I mean, technically, when the COVID
situation started, right, when the whole
country went into a lockdown, and in fact,
when the whole world pretty much went into
a lockdown, I mean, technically that's an
issue.
That was an issue.
However, in the weeks leading up to that,
we still had this risk, right?
We still had some knowledge
that, you know, there was
this pandemic or potential
of a pandemic coming along.
And so, you know, we could identify,
I mean, a week or so a week or two weeks
before the actual lockdown, we were told
that there might be a lockdown coming.
So, again, it was an uncertainty.
At that point, project managers did not
really have the authority to make a lot of
decisions about the project at that point,
right?
Should we shut the project down?
would put it on hold or what do we do,
that's going to be escalated to senior
management, or rather that would have been
escalated to senior management.
So another strategy then is avoid.
Now avoid does not mean ignore,
right?
Avoid means eliminate.
You eliminate the risk, right?
You eliminate it.
So it's no longer a risk anymore.
That is an avoid.
So as a simple example, let's say we want
to outsource this activity, right,
got this one activity, I want to outsource
it.
I want to outsource it to our preferred
vendor.
You know, we've worked
with this preferred vendor
many times before and,
you know, they're really good.
That's why they're a preferred vendor.
So we want to outsource it to this
preferred vendor.
However, this preferred vendor also has a
trade union, or rather
trade union workers.
They have a trade union population.
And we've been hearing rumors,
you know, there might, You know,
there's been some disagreements.
They might end up going on strike.
We don't want to deal with that.
They go on strike halfway through the
project.
That's going to have a big, huge,
major impact on our project.
We do not want to deal with that.
So, we decide instead to eliminate that
risk altogether.
So let's do the work ourselves.
Or we outsource it to
another organization, another
vendor that doesn't have
a trade union population.
So now we've eliminated that risk,
they're not going to go on strike.
However, there's another
term I want to mention here, not
mentioned in this slide, but it is
mentioned in a subsequent slide.
You may come across something called a
secondary risk, right?
So let's say, in this case,
we outsource it to a different
vendor that doesn't have
a trade union population.
So now they're not going to go on strike,
we've eliminated that risk altogether.
However, we might have introduced what's
known as a secondary risk.
And a secondary risk is as a result of any
of these risk response strategies,
be it a negative risk or even any of the
positive risks.
There might be a new risk that's been
identified that wasn't there before.
So the very simple example then.
We outsource it to a different vendor.
We haven't worked with this vendor before.
vendor might not be up to the Mark,
right?
That vendor might not be,
you know, might have a much
longer learning curve
and so and so forth, right?
I mean, you know, there's many factors.
There's many risks that you might identify
there or several risks that might identify
there because we haven't worked with this
vendor before.
Those would be known as a secondary risk.
So any of these risk
response strategies could
result in a new risk
that wasn't there before.
That's known as a secondary risk.
Another strategy is transfer.
And transfer means shifting it to a third
party.
Right, deflecting it, shifting it to a
third party.
Let them deal with it.
Most common example of that is buying
insurance.
Anything happens, insurance company is
going to pay.
That would be an example of a transfer.
Or let's say there is some dangerous
activities and these activities could
potentially cause physical harm to your
team members.
So you decide, we don't want to deal with
that.
Let's outsource it to a
vendor, to a company that
specializes in those kind
of dangerous activities.
So now we have transferred the risk to the
third party.
Now, be very careful with transfer,
though, because even though you've
transferred that risk, this is still your
project.
You're a project manager.
This is still your project.
So you still own part of that risk.
So what's your division of responsibility
of the risk and the third party,
the vendor's division of responsibility of
the risk?
That's all documented in the contract.
That's all part of the contract.
So that's a very simple example.
If you buy insurance, you have a
deductible.
That's your division of responsibility of
the risk.
The rest of it is insurance companies.
Another strategy is mitigate.
A mitigate means either or both, reducing
the impact or reducing the probability.
Either reducing the impact of the risk or
reducing the probability.
So just a very simple
example then, wearing a
mask during our COVID-19
pandemic situation.
That's going to reduce the probability of
the virus spreading.
That's not going to eliminate it,
but it's going to reduce the probability.
Or another strategy would be reducing the
impact.
So let's say we have a key technical
analyst on our project and the success of
this technical analyst is,
or rather the success of
the project is based on
this key technical analyst.
If this person leaves, the whole project
is going to come to a standstill.
So we decide let's cross-train all of our
different team members so that they can
perform one task that this technical
analyst can perform.
So that in the event, if this technical
analyst leaves, then at least the rest of
our team can perform
one activity, one task
that this technical analyst can perform.
And so our project is still moving along.
It's not, you know, it's not the best case
scenario, right?
It's still chugging along, still moving
along.
But at least it doesn't come to a
standstill.
Not the best case scenario, but not the
worst case scenario either.
And that is exactly what a mitigate is.
A mitigate is always never the best case,
never the worst case.
But at least we've made something.
At least we made some kind of decision.
Or you could accept it altogether.
And accept basically means living with the
risk.
All right, there's a risk there.
All right, we'll figure it out.
Now, there's two types of acceptance,
though.
You have something called an active
acceptance and a passive acceptance.
Active acceptance is specifically put in,
money aside in contingency reserve, right?
So all that talk that we've had
regarding contingency reserve,
that is when you have been
actively accepting the risk.
We've actively accepted it, right?
We can't avoid, transfer, mitigate, so we
put some money aside
in contingency reserve.
Or if it's a schedule impact, right,
we could add in a scheduling buffer.
That scheduling buffer would be considered
the schedule contingency reserve,
if you like.
So everything then, all that talk
we've had regarding contingency
reserve is when you have
been actively accepting the risk.
A passive acceptance, on the other hand,
is literally do nothing.
We'll figure it out if it happens.
That is a passive acceptance.
I wouldn't necessarily ignore it,
but you know, you've identified the risk.
We're not going to do anything about it.
We'll figure it out.
If it happens, then we'll do something
about it.
Or we're passively accepting it right now.
We don't know what to do right now.
So let's observe this risk and maybe we
can think closer and closer as,
say, you know, the probability starts
increasing.
Okay.
So these are all the strategies then for a
negative risk.
And just a very quick exam strategy here.
If the first thing, in a question,
they'll give a scenario.
First thing you have to determine is it's
a positive risk or a negative risk,
right?
Because there's
different terminology for a
positive risk, which is
covered in a separate slide.
If it's a negative risk and
you see positive risk terms,
then you know immediately
you can eliminate those.
If it's a best case scenario,
if the strategy that you've
taken is a best case scenario,
then that would be a void.
you've completely eliminated the risk
altogether.
If it's the worst-case scenario,
you haven't done anything about it,
that would be a passive acceptance.
If somewhere in the scenario, it states
something about risk reserves,
you know, budget, you put extra money
aside in your budget, contingency reserve,
then that's an active acceptance.
If there's a third party
involved, right, a vendor
involved, then
immediately that's a transfer.
If you've done something, it's neither the
best case nor the worst case, but you've
done something about it, then that would
be a mitigate.
So just a little exam hint, exam tip
there.